A Guide to the Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files, 1941-1942
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the President of the University of Virginia, Office Administrative Files 1941-1942
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
RG-2/1/2.531
This collection consists of 6,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Access restrictions may apply to specific student records under the terms of the Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (F.E.R.P.A.).
Scope and Content Information
These files constitute the major record series generated by the president of the University of Virginia. The records consist chiefly of correspondence, but also include reports, minutes, clippings, memoranda, and related papers concerning all areas of business of the president's office.
Contents List
- General Files, 1941-1942
  - "A" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Alderman, Mrs.--personal letters, mainly signed "Mama" 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Investments 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Board--Treasurer 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Office--Alderman Alumni Fund Council 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Office--Allotments from Contingent Fund 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Office--Alumni Board of Trustees of the UVa. Endowment Fund 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Alumni Office--General Correspondence 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - American Council on Education: American Association of University Professors, American Peace Society, History of Science Society, American Arbitration Society, American Association of Political and Social Science 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - American Society of Civil Engineers 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Annual Reports 1941-1942 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions (2 folders) 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Art and Architecture 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Art Commission 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Art, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Association of American Colleges 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Association of American Universities 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Association of Virginia Colleges 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Astronomy, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Athletics 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - "B" Miscellaneous (1 of 2)--correspondence re: Page-Barbour lectures; Paul Barringer correspondence re: Law Library needs; J. Barron II correspondence re: Naval History in N.C. 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - "B" Miscellaneous (2 of 2) 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Bayly Art Museum 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Biblical History and Literature 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Biology, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Biology, Department of--Blandy Farm--records, history, report of the committee 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Biology, Department of--Mountain Lake 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Box Bushes--Stettinius' gift of 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Campbell House 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Cemetery 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Commons 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Faculty Housing 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Fuel 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--General 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Home for Crippled Children 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Library 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Personnel 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Roads 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Scott Stadium 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Buildings and Grounds--Special Rooms--"Salle Lafayette" 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Building Program--Architects and Engineers 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Building Program--Incinerator 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Building Program--Medical Buildings 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Building Program--Naval R.O.T.C. 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Building Program--Power Plant and Heating Mains 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Bursar's Office 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - "C" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Carnegie Corporation--Money for Music Department; Randall Thompson and Mrs. Tuttle 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Carnegie Foundation for the Advancement of Teaching 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Cavalier Daily--see College Topics1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Cavalier Daily-- College Topics Questionnaire 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Chemistry, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Chemistry, Department of--Dr. Ross 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Church Society for College Work--report 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Commerce and Business Administration 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Public Occasions--Atcheson Hench, chair 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Commons 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Convocations--Speakers: Alan Valentine, Gordon Chalmers 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - "D" Miscellaneous--correspondence of Virginius Dabney re: the University and the South 1941-1942 (Box 4)
  - Dean Ferguson--papers re: Committee on Academic Legislation 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Dean Lewis--description of Easter week (Easters) 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - DuPont Trust 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - "E" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Education, Department of--General 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Education, State Board of 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Emergency Committee in Aid of Displaced Foreign Scholars 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Engineering, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - English Department 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - Extension Division--Drama 'taught thru' state; Wm. Smith manuscript sent to Rockefeller Foundation 1941-1942 (Box 5)
  - "F" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Faculty--lists 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Fellowships and Scholarships--General 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Finals 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Forestry 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Seward Forest 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Forms 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Founder's Day (1941)--speaker, Pierre de Lanux 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Founder's Day (1942)--speaker, Dixon Ryan Fox 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - "G" Miscellaneous--Galt sketches for statue of Jefferson given by nieces of Galt; Glazebrook, first tennis courts at UVa. 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - General Education Board 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Geological Survey 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Geology, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - German, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 6)
  - Governor's Office (2 folders) 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Graduate Department 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Greek, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - "H" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - History, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Honor Committee 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Honor System 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - "I" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Institute of International Education 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Institute of Public Affairs--Wendell Wilkie speaking, introduced by President Newcomb 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Institute of Public Affairs--contributors 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Institute of Public Affairs--council 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Insurance--hospitalization--study 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Interracial Cooperation Commission 1941-1942 (Box 7)
  - Invitations to be refused 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - "J" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - Jefferson Bicentennial or Birthday Plans 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - Jefferson Items--statue by Rudulph Evans; violin (Amati) offered to UVa. (violin, statue, cane) 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - "K" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - "L" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - Latin 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - Law, Department of--Library (Union catalogue); Dean Ribble appointed to Court of Appeals; W. H. White; Frances Farmer, librarian; Ribble correspondence; Marshall Portrait to Richmond; binding program 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - Lectures 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - Richard Lectures 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - Legal Papers--W. A. Perkins, attorney 1941-1942 (Box 8)
  - Library--Alderman 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - Library--McGregor 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - Legislative Program 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - "M" Miscellaneous--correspondence of Mayhoff, Mrs. re: Deed to Monticello 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - Madison Hall 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - Mathematics 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - McIntire Fund 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - Medicine, Department of--Dean Jordan 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - Medicine, Department of--addition to Urology Department 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - Medicine, Department of (1 of 2)--Hospital--Ward Patient Reports 1941-1942 (Box 9)
  - Medicine, Department of (2 of 2)--Hospital--Ward Patient Reports 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Medicine, Department of--Interns' Quarters 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Medicine, Department of--Rucker Convalescent Home for Crippled Children 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Medicine, Department of--Student Health Service 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Music--correspondence of Randall Thompson 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - "N" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - National Association of State Universities--University of Wyoming case 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - National Youth Administration 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Naval Academy Board 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - "O" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - "P" Miscellaneous--Pi Delta Epsilon, petition for course in journalism turned down 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Phi Beta Kappa--revised constitution 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Philosophy 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Physical Education, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Physics, Department of--Mr. Sparrows book to be published; replacement for Mr. Sparrow is sought; Strauss report on high voltage presented 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Political Science, Department of--notes difficulty in replacing men in service 1941-1942 (Box 10)
  - Psychology, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - Public Administration, Bureau of 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - Public Speaking, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - Questionnaire 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - "R" Miscellaneous--Rosenwald Fund--lists recipients both black and white; Raven Society--new members 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - Recommendation, Letters of (2 folders) 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - Requisitions 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - Romance Languages, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - Rural Social Economics, School of --reports from Blacksburg and UVa. 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - "S" Miscellaneous (1 of 3)--President Sanger of Medical College of Virginia: plans joint communications with UVa. to promote cooperation; Selective Service: in all fields above; Survey of Albemarle and adjacent counties 1941-1942 (Box 11)
  - "S" Miscellaneous (2 of 3) 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - "S" Miscellaneous (3 of 3)--Stettinius letters--ca. 30 letters re: boxwoods; war posters; Belgian Stock. acceptance to Board of Visitors; resignation from Board of William and Mary 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - Senate--University--gives plans for vacations and academic credit 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - Sigma Xi 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - Sociology, Department of 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - Southern University Conference 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - Speeches 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - State Supported Institutions--Association of Presidents 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - State University Association 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - Statistics 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - Sullivan Awards--discussed 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - Summer Quarter workshop in education is planned 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - "T" Miscellaneous--Tunstall, Robert--correspondence; Trigg, R. P.--public health course for blacks and whites needed 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - "U" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - United States Office of Education 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - "V" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 12)
  - Virginia Bureau of Industrial Research--Records and Reports 1941-1942 (Box 13)
  - Virginia Quarterly Review--war-time difficulties due to leaves; final break with Dutton 1941-1942 (Box 13)
  - Visitors--General Correspondence (2 folders) 1941-1942 (Box 13)
  - Visitors--Finance Communications 1941-1942 (Box 13)
  - "W" Miscellaneous--Wallace, Henry--speech; Weddell, Alexander--publication of "Life of Jane Porter"; Wertenbaker, Thomas--correspondence 1941-1942 (Box 13)
  - Woodrow Wilson Birthplace Foundation 1941-1942 (Box 13)
  - Women, Dean of 1941-1942 (Box 13)
  - "X-Y-Z" Miscellaneous 1941-1942 (Box 13)